{
  "reference_number": "9155",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "With technology changes it may be possible to advance net zero date, as such there should be more flexibility to set the date"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Carbon dioxide levels are only part of the problem, other harmful gases and pollutants must be reduced as well"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New Zealand should not rely on other countries to reduce emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes if other methods can be found to be more successful in reducing the rate of climate change or the date could be moved forward."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes there needs to be clear short term targets, provided they are realistic and achievable."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There should be flexibility to revise budgets according to circumstances. Governments can and do change the law and targets. This\n question is a waste of space."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be flexibility to revise budgets according to circumstances. Governments can and do change the law and targets. This\nquestion is a waste of space."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Need to take into account events such as earthquakes, volcanic activity and other events that may make delay achieving targets so\n\nthat budgets are meaningless. Should also include population growth which has a significant impact on carbon levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Need plan to achieve goals, so these should be outline in the bill, but do not need to be detailed."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Ensuring they are are realistic and achievable in the time frame."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I disagree with Emissions Trading. I believe Carbon use should be taxed. With some carbon sequestering efforts being given grants or\n\ntax reduction."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I disagree with Emissions Trading. I believe Carbon use should be taxed. With some carbon sequestering efforts being given grants or\ntax reduction."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There is consideration of Maori values, but not of the values for other races why?"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Unless the government is proposing another bill. Adaption to climate change is more important than zero carbon, there is not point in"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Should Including need to be prepared for climate changes in resource management act and building regulations. There is no point in\n\nallowing long term building on land that is expected to be flooded without adequate flood prevention measures."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Need to be able see that progress is being made"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The minister opens the discussion paper with references to the adverse impacts, but makes resolving them optional. The focus of\n\nthe government should be about action to adapt to climate change which is needed much sooner than trying to reduce the rate of\nchange which is a more long term goal."
    }
  ]
}
